MARK L CHAVES

Email Phone

mark@marklchaves.com +62 811 38 000 65

SUMMARY

Mark is a freelance photographer, writer, and web developer. Before becoming a freelancer, Mark worked more than twenty years as a software **engineer** and application development **manager** with startups and Fortune 500 companies.

Mark's main goal is to **lead** a web development, content creation, or software product team.

EXPERIENCE

MARK L CHAVES caughtmyeve.dev

Ubud Bali, Indonesia January 2015-Present Freelance Photographer, Writer, and Web Developer

- Freelance photographer for Loop Images, UK.
- · Freelance photographer for Airbnb Plus.
- Founder of Bali Street Photographer Pasar Ubud Tours.
- Independent contributor to online & print publications such as inBali.org, Air Asia Travel 3Sixty, & Asian Geographic.
- Editor for Vimpt.com.
- Freelance web developer designing/building/maintaining websites built on WordPress, Squarespace, and Jekyll.
- Freelance content creator for solopreneurs, small businesses, and NGOs.

Independent IT and Leadership Consultant

- Lead and facilitate learning and development programmes on effective communications, time management, leadership, and Agile methodologies for Bank of America/Merrill Lynch, attorneys, and NGOs.
- Provide IT support as a virtual assistant for creating and maintaining WordPress websites; designing and launching email campaigns; and developing marketing content.
- Editor for the editorr.com application.

COMO HOTELS & RESORTS

Paro, Bhutan June 2014-January 2015

Ubud Bali, Indonesia September 2011-June 2014

Consultant and Program Manager

- Designed, delivered, and maintained programs and activities at COMO Shambhala Estate Ubud, Bali.
- Part of the Condé Nast and SpaFinder Asia award-winning team 2011-2013.
- Provided regional consulting services to COMO's teams in Bhutan, Maldives, and Thailand.
- Managed a multi-disciplinary team of consultants, instructors, and local guides.
- Initiated service-oriented leadership, dynamic collaboration, and continual process evolution methodologies to improve productivity, quality, and team morale.

SONY PLAYSTATION

San Diego, CA USA May 2008-August 2011 Senior Manager of Application Development and Global Cloud Hosting Services

- Role: Sr. Application Development Manager
 - Responsibilities included: managing a team of developers,

MARK L CHAVES

mark@marklchaves.com

testers, and writers; implementing SCRUM to support rapid development of web applications built with Ruby on Rails on a LAMP stack with Oracle; liaising with infrastructure teams and online game development studios; and conducting sustainable performance management to cultivate a highly effective team.

- Customers included global project teams and game development studios internal and external to Sony Online Entertainment.
- Impact: Successfully merged a young team of web app developers with game QA engineers to create a highly effective product development team that achieved high team retention rates and increased productivity by approximately 400% within 1.5 years.
- Role: Sr. Global Hosting Manager
 - Responsibilities included: managing a team of Unix system administrators and cloud hosting engineers to host Sony PLayStation online titles for the Americas, and collaborating with game development studio heads.
 - Customers included the heads of all game development studios under the Sony Online Entertainment umbrella.
 - Impact: Introduced ground breaking OpenStack technology that enabled 1) the turn-around of an unprofitable team with low customer happiness and low internal morale to become in-demand by Sony's largest studios, 2) improved team retention, 3) surprisingly the creation of a queue for engineers wanting to transfer into the team, and 4) the senior engineers to step into the spotlight by presenting their work along side RackSpace Corp to our industry peers in a global cloud hosting conference.

LA FITNESS

Irvine, CA USA July 2007-May 2008

ÉLAN PHARMACEUTICALS

San Diego, CA USA May 2003-December 2007

Product Manager LAFitness.com

- Led the .Net development team that supported the design, development, testing, and operations for LAFitness.com.
- Used Microsoft's Visual Studio IDE to build and manage the C# codebase.

Senior Technical Manager R&D

- Managed a team of engineers, developers, testers, tech writers, and operational support personnel that were responsible for customizing a Documentum/CoreDossier/eCTDXpress system used for R&D drug submissions to the FDA.
- Implemented SOX compliance.
- Led FDA validation projects based on PMI project management methodologies and training.
- Impact: successfully reorganized the IT team to handle
 multiple development and operations projects using effective
 division of labour delegation, which increased productivity and
 ability to takeover the operations of more applications without
 increasing the team's size.

HUMAN GENOME

Senior Software Engineer R&D

MARK L CHAVES

SCIENCES Development lead and project manager supporting biotech R&D teams for drug submissions. January 2001-April 2003 Senior architect and team lead implementing J2EE/Oracle applications using UML and RUP. Impact: introduced UML and RUP to breakthrough stalled business analysis initiatives and attract highly skilled OO developers. Director of Engineering NEXTSTRAT (startup) Managed site operations and customer engagements. January 1999-December Managed a team of software engineers, testers, network 2001 engineers, DBAs, and technical writers. Developed strategy planning and management software for American Express Corporation. Supported executive level presentations, consultations, and strategic planning sessions. Impact: contributed to the successful buyout of the company. ORACLE CORPORATION Principal Consultant and Senior Software Engineer Member of the original WebDB team that developed the first web app for the Oracle RDBMS. January 1999-December 1999 Original developer for Oracle's first web-based online help system. Original developer of PL/SQLdoc. Champion of J2EE and XML technologies. COMMUNITY Senior Software Engineer NETWORKS INC. (startup) Developer for a web-based community portal application deployed on cable set-top boxes. January 1997-January Wrote code in Java, JavaScript, and HTML. 1999 **BOLT, BERANEK, &** Computer Scientist R&D NEWMAN (BBN) Conducted R&D on classified artificial intelligence systems. Pioneered the use of JavaScript Beta (cutting edge) to support June 1996-January 1997 rapid application development (RAD). Software Engineer Top Secret Projects and Simulations INTERNATIONAL **BUSINESS MACHINES**

- Role: Technical lead for structured and newly formed object oriented development projects.
- Responsibilities: conducted Shlaer Mellor OOA/D using IDEs on IBM AIX (Unix) workstations; developed rapid prototype simulations in C++.
- Impact: Member of the first IBM team to use 1) Java (v1.05), 2) a OODBMS, 3) design patterns, and 4) UML/RUP.

EDUCATION Masters of Computer Science, American University, Washington, DC, USA, May 2002

Bachelor of Science, School of Engineering, The Ohio State University, Columbus, OH, USA, March 1992

Associate of Arts, University of Maryland European Division, UK, 1988

(IBM)

May 1992-June 1996

QUALIFICATIONS

- 20+ years of experience in global product development for Fortune 500 and startup companies in the software, biotech, and online entertainment industries.
- Development manager focused on cultivating highly effective self-managed teams with an emphasis on stakeholder engagement and transparency.
- Structured and Agile project manager with a proven track record of completing milestones on time and on budget.
- Agile development champion with hands-on experience using methodologies such as eXtreme programming, RUP, and SCRUM.
- Promoted people first leadership. Encouraged highly collaborative environments with knowledge sharing supported by cloud-based applications such as Asana, Trello, Jira, Github, Basecamp, Amazon AWS, Documentum, and MS Sharepoint.
- Object oriented analysis and design using Shlaer Mellor and UML.
- Programming languages: & technologies: WordPress, HTML5, CSS3, AMP, PWA, SEO, Jekyll, Liquid, Git, Ruby on Rails, C#, Java, PHP, JavaScript ES6, C++/C, PL/SQL, Perl, and various Unix shell scripting languages.
- Industries: Software, Gaming/Entertainment, Biotech/Pharmaceutical, Finance, Communications, Defence, Government, NGO, Fitness, and Hospitality.

VOLUNTEER

- Mission Paws'ible Freelance Photographer and WordPress consultant, Bali, 2018-present
- Bali Spirit Festival Freelance Photographer, Bali, 2018
- Large Marine Vertebrates Research Institute Philippines (LAMAVE) Fundraising Project Manager, Cebu Philippines, February 2015
- Outdoor Outreach Rock Climbing, Surfing, and Snowboard Instructor for at-risk youth, San Diego, 2007-2010

LANGUAGES

- English: native language
- Indonesian: basic to intermediate proficiency